<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Jesuits grand design upon England, clearly discovered in a letter lately written from a father of that society.</title>
            <author>Peirce, Edmund, Sir, d. 1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90362</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1019_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208327</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867285</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867285</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119590</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90362)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119590)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 151:E1019[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Jesuits grand design upon England, clearly discovered in a letter lately written from a father of that society.</title>
                  <author>Peirce, Edmund, Sir, d. 1667.</author>
                  <author>J. M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. Attributed by Wing to Sir Edmond Peirce.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: J.M.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "April. 4.1660".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  Controversial literature --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119590:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE JESUITS GRAND DESIGN UPON ENGLAND, Clearly diſcovered in a Letter lately written from a Father of that Society.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Received your laſt, and have ſent the incloſed to the party according as you deſired. Monſieur <hi>De-vaulx</hi> came hither laſt night from <hi>Lyons,</hi> where he met with Monſieur <hi>Prè</hi> who was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſt from <hi>Rome</hi> (where he hath been ever ſince the death of the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> his great friend and benefactor) to <hi>Germany;</hi> he ſaith he is like to repair the loſs he had by the Dukes death, with an imployment which an <hi>Italian</hi> Cardinall will help him to; I am glad of it, for although the man have none of the acuteſt parts, he hath heen very active and induſtrious, and hath done (to my knowledge) no ſmall ſervices. He ſaith that ſome Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees in thoſe parts are not ſo much joyed with the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> death, as it was ſuppoſed they would; I could partly gueſſe the cauſe, but referring that to another opportunity, I ſhall at preſent enlarge my ſelf concerning what is now the greateſt trouble and care to us all: The ſtate of things in <hi>England,</hi> which truly I am very ſorry to hear how it dayly grows worſe and worſe: For although you ſeem not to apprehend ſo much, becauſe as you write, if things ſhould come to a ſettlement there, that you could not think the Catholicks to be in a much worſe condition; becauſe you ſuppoſe it would be then, as in former times, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lawes concerning their Eſtates not to be put in ſo rigorous an execution as now, and that they had rather be in ſome certain way under the Government of one, whoſe prudence and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119590:2"/>was well known, then ſtill to be expoſed to the Frantick mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of what ever happens to be uppermoſt, who upon all occaſion, link them with their greateſt enemies, in all mulcts of puniſhment; And who can never be ſuppoſed with any face to ſhew the leaſt favour to them; And that it is the opinion of ſome ſober men, that their caſe (if there were once a ſettlement) in ſome Parliament, might deſerve ſome conſideration as to penall Laws, which were made in a conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of time, when ſeverity was requiſite, and the Kingdom exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by (I muſt needs ſay) very deſperate attempts; but ſeeing in ſo long a tract of time, the party is much wafted, and made inconſiderable in whatever might make them formidable: And they have not a long while been guilty of any exorbitant offence, and that the intereſt of the King would be rather to compoſe and court all parties, then exaſperate any: You (I ſay) for theſe reaſons do ſuppoſe our condition there, would be rather better then worſe.</p>
            <p>I muſt needs confeſſe that there is ſome ground for your opinion, as to the Engliſh Catholicks of eſtate and fortunes, and who by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence cannot but have much of the Nations true intereſt in them, and poſſibly as to their particular had better be ſettled in ſome moderate way, then in ſuch condition, as if things come to that paſſe, which we ſo long have driven at, for advancing the generall cauſe of the Church, which perhaps by reaſon of your years you have not ſo fully under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and which only (neglecting all other particulars) is a grand du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a true ſon of the Catholick Church, and how far we were all here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in concerned as to the affaires of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For you muſt know that about twenty years agoe the Engliſh Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks had brought their Church to ſuch a height, and ſettled it in ſo fair and plauſible a way, the Doctrine of it ſo learnedly maintained by their Divines; Men (I muſt needs ſay) moſt of them of admirable learning and parts, whatſoever we could object to them ſtill ſo fully anſwered, Their Diſcipline ſuch, as did dayly give ſatisfaction to more and more of all parties, Their Ceremonies being decent and comely, for the moſt part grounded upon Scripture, or the ancient cuſtoms of the Primitive Church; Inſomuch that many who were offended with the multiplicity, inſignificancy, and ſuperſtition which they apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in ours, did much better like of them; For (I muſt needs ſay (as I think I have ſometimes told you before) we did retain many things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we thought it more prudent to alter nothing at all, rather then that ſome could be ſolidly maintained, thinking it better with wit and art bravely to bear them out, then by yeelding to the leaſt alteration
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119590:2"/>(which once begun we could perhaps never have ſtay'd) breed any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repute or diſhonour to our Church; And finally all things ſettled in that ſplendid and orderly way, under ſo potent and conſiderable a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, that as it was the powerfull head and protector of all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Churches in the world; ſo likely to be the great countenancer and procurer of any new revolt, which in ſome conſiderable ſtates, was feared, and in veryſhort time probable to gain ground upon, if not quite over-throw the Catholick Church; Inſomuch that as, then thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations (to my knowledge) there was nothing more terrible to us; ſo, then that, which was afterwards the occaſion of diſſipating theſe fears nothing more welcome: Although it was no more then we might ever ſomewhat probably alſo expect, as we have from time to time car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed on affaires there by our Agents, we knowing well that there was alwayes in <hi>England</hi> a numerous ſort of well meaning men, who did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſerve God in a perfect way, as their conſciences inſtructed as they were) informed them. Theſe being moſt of them of indifferent wealth, and of a middle degree and capacity, and therefore few of them being capable to apprehend the main ſcope and deſign of the Rulers of their Church, but being (I cannot tell how) perſwaded (to the no ſmall laughter of us you muſt imagine) that the way their Biſhops then went was in order to favour, if not quite bring in the Catholick Religion, and being not a little heighthned in ſuch their fancies by our indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble endeavours, They began at length to prove very troubleſome, and in ſome good ſort to anſwer our expectations. The Univerſities like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſwarming then with men of excellent learning and parts, it was a hard matter for one, who was not therein eminent, to attain (if not well befriended) to any conſiderable preferment. Hence it was that they which had loytered their time, when they could live no longer there, uſually ſeated themſelves in ſome populous Town, in which were great numbers of the aforeſaid people, then called Puritans, from whom (by reaſon of ſome Lecture) they having their maintenance, their preaching was ſuch, as was moſt likely to get credit with that party. Hence were their Sermons commonly invectives againſt the preſent or-orders of the Church. And the more they were taken notice of by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, the more were they flocked after, and grew to greater emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, and thereby had occaſion of gaining a greater number of Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites to their opinion, ſo that in time ſome Thouſands there were, which were deſperately bent againſt their Church government. Theſe (as we ordered the matter) being made uſe of by ſome perſons of quality and ability, who being diſcontented upon private occaſions, or elſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119590:3"/>thinking they had no preferments anſwerable to their merits, and many things (too long to relate) then conſpiring together, and driving af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires to that exigence, that it was not in the power of the wiſeſt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, did in ſome ſhort time (which your years might then begin to take notice of) quite confound that, which (as I ſaid before) was ſo dreadfull to us. For now the Engliſh Church, which before was ſo much the object of our fear, was onely fit for our contempt and ſcorn: whilſt we ſaw nothing but confuſion, ſuch infinite diviſions, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny frantick Sectaries ſtill ſwarming and countenanced, ſo that we could not poſſibly expect any the leaſt inconvenience from thence: Nay, we could not in all prudence, but in a little time ſuppoſe thoſe ſtrange di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions would afford ſome potent Prince of our Religion an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to get conſiderable footing in that Nation: Or elſe that ſome uſurper, who not altogether relying upon the inconſtant and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſupport of an Army, might ſtrike in with the Pope, and ſtrengthen himſelf with his, and all our Intereſts. A thing to my knowledge that hath not been altogether unattempted by you know who, in either of which caſes our ends had in ſome good meaſure been accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems the Generality of the Nation, are made by all theſe ſtrange viciſſitudes of miſery, that they have of late run through, ſo fully to underſtand their condition, that they do with their utmoſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour endeavour the freeing themſelves from that force and Tyranny under which they have ſo long groaned, in order to the obtaining a firm compoſure of things, and re-ſetling their Church; which truly I am in much doubt they may poſſibly bring about, and ſo fruſtrate our grand and chief deſign.</p>
            <p>For although there be many ſtrange kind of diviſions amongſt them, yet the conſiderable, wealthy, and potent part of the Nation, are for the moſt part but of two ſorts, that is to ſay, the Royal Party, and the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> between whom, although we have uſed all the art that can be imagined to create an everlaſting jealouſie and enmity; yet we have great cauſe to fear that they may poſſibly come to ſome good cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence. For the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> have been made ſenſible, that they two being ſuch conſiderable Parties, neither of them are able to eſtabliſh any thing like to laſt, if either of them oppoſe. And although the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> did at the beginning, ſome things, which many have thought to have been the cauſe of what after hapned; yet 'tis long ſince mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly known that publick actings were, by the prevalency of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondents then mixed amongſt them (whom I ſuppoſe you know) carryed a great deal further then their intentions, which at the firſt no
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119590:3"/>doubt were ſomewhat moderate, although they were ſtill ſurprized and hurried on by that party from one thing to another, as the urgency of affairs required, and in order at length to their own preſervation: And that they did much endeavour the compoſure of things, and were in the midſt of ſuch endeavours, when the Army acted thoſe high exorbitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, quite contrary to their minds, and to the amazement and grief of moſt of them. None are ignorant, as alſo that many of them thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſundry others, by the ſince loyall endeavours of that party were made fellow ſufferers with the <hi>Royaliſts.</hi> And for the matter of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the difference is not ſo great, as ſome animoſities of the parties have made them: They agreeing in moſt ſubſtantials, And their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines on both ſides being men of Learning and Reaſon, (heates layd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and both parties moderated by the experience of ſo much afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) ſome healing temper perhaps not yet thought on, may probably be found out: That they can have no reaſon to believe the <hi>King</hi> ſhould bear them the leaſt regret, ſeeing the premiſes are not onely notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but alſo many of them that were once eminently active againſt him and his Father, are now become his greateſt confidents. And if his mild and gentle nature were not ſo manifeſtly known to be unapt to harbour thoughts of revenge; Yet his affairs being in ſuch a condition as they are, he cannot be ſuppoſed in any prudence to diſoblige ſo potent a party, but rather that it muſt needs be many years before he can bring the Nation to that firmneſs of ſettlement, that he may with any ſafety exaſperate, or ſlight the moſt inconſiderable faction. And that the Royal Party likewiſe, would be ſo far from having any memory of things paſt, that if they might but once come to that free condition that the other ſubjects of the Nation are in, without any more fear of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement, impriſonment, or mulcts peculiar to them, and reſtored to a capacity of bearing ſome ſhare equally with others in the Government; that they would think themſelves in a happy condition without raveling into former buſineſſes of any kind, the forgetting whereof on all hands, being moſt abſolutely neceſſary to a future peace. Theſe conſiderations, (as I have lately heard from a credible hand) have made ſuch an impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> that I doubt there is no little cauſe to fear that all our practiſes to hinder the aforeſaid reconciliation will prove ineffectual; our utmoſt endeavour (however) muſt not yet be omitted; and ſomewhat was done lately to that purpoſe by good advice, which I hope by this time is publiſhed as a Letter ſent from <hi>Bruxels,</hi> that affaire being put into ſuch hands, as 'tis known will do it to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And although we have alſo been in hopes that the Army joyning
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119590:4"/>with theſe Sectaries, (who it ſeems have got a new name, and are now called <hi>Phanatiques</hi>) would ſtrenuouſly endeavour to make ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable new diſturbance, being inſtructed, that if there ſhould once happen to be a compoſure, that they would abſolutely be disbanded, or at leaſt remain in no power, credit, or countenance at all; And many of their Officers, having ſhares in the Kings and Biſhops Lands, cannot but think that in ſuch caſe they muſt needs loſe them: yet I have heard likewiſe, that they have been much quieted, and appeaſed by ſome, who have made them underſtand their preſent, true, and beſt intereſt; And have repreſented to them, that although in the concluſion of that ſharp warre, wherein all the active ſpirits of the Nation were almoſt deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the whole Kingdom in a conſternation with their great ſucceſs, which was indeed as much to be attributed to the diſorders and negligence of the other party, as their own valour and conduct. Their Body likewiſe then far more conſiderable for number then now they are, and for ſome years quartered together, and thereby, with the extraordinary politique endeavours, and practiſes of as able an head as any this latter age af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded, made all of one mind, They made a ſhift to carry on a deſign, and bear it very high for a while, yet (that which all ſober and ſerious perſons could not but conjecture at firſt) partly with their own (not long after) diſagreement, which did neceſſarily ariſe, and the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of others, did many times ſtagger, and finally run it ſelf into ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, that had all the ſaid wily devices continued with the life of the Protector <hi>Oliver,</hi> it could not in all likelyhood have ſtood much lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, And that now they have notoriouſly loſt much of their repute: For when they pulled down <hi>Richard,</hi> it was viſible to the whole Nation, they were in no ſort able to carry on their intended work; but were forced to ſet up for a preſent ſhift thoſe members, that now for ſome while in <hi>England</hi> are ſo famouſly known by name of the <hi>Rump,</hi> who in a very ſhort ſpace, had almoſt ruined them. And not long after, when they turned thoſe out, they were far more at a loſſe then before. They (not without much difficulty, making good their ground in <hi>London,</hi> where, if they had been but never ſo little more baffled, they had utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been ruined) were beat out of ſeverall Towns in the Countrey, and no doubt in ſome little time, had been utterly wearied out, if not quite torn in pieces, even by the diſorderly, tumultuous, and disarmed rabble. But now, that they are in no conſiderable Bodies together, nor can have no great confidence of one another, there being ſuch endeavours uſed, whereby their leaſt attempts of ſeditious communication (if any be) are diſcovered, and that perhaps by ſome whom themſelves little think of,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119590:4"/>The Nation alſo having recovered infinite courage and heart, thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of men of ſpirit able to carry on buſineſs, being grown up, who were but children in former tranſactions, and ſcarce remember, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are not ſenſible of the dread of thoſe things, which have been the greateſt cauſe of keeping others ſo quiet. Not a County almoſt in the poſture it is in, but being able to hinder their greateſt attempt. Such a formidable Militia in <hi>London,</hi> which in very few years might be increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to thrice the number, beſides ſo diſciplined, experienced, and choyce a body, as the Generalls Souldiers are. They cannot in reaſon expect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſucceſs, or ſhould they beyond their expectation have it, they could hope for nothing but to make ſome buſle or diſturbance for a while, the conſequence whereof, they themſelves know not, and in moſt probability would ſtill prove worſe and worſe to themſelves, as thoſe they have made already, have alwayes done.</p>
            <p>But ſhould they in the leaſt meaſure be worſted in any ſuch enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, no people in the world would be more miſerable then they, the hatred that the Nation hath already conceived againſt them upon that occaſion likely to be ſo aggravated, that in every corner thereof they would find the effects of their fury, whereas if they behave themſelves peaceably, they cannot but be honourably dealt withall; the enſuing Parliament being likely to make ſuch proviſions for them, whereby the quiet of the Nation ſhould not be hazarded by any ſuch their deſperate and vaine attemps. And as to their purchaſes, they being in the ſame condition with others, and many of the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> in the ſame ſtate too, the Parliament cannot but find out ſome expedient (as many already are thought on) to content all perſons, nor can it be ſuppoſed they will ſuffer ſo great a number as are concerned in thoſe lands to be diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed. And laſtly they, having given ſuch ample teſtimony of their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and ability to ſerve their Country, will in all likelyhood be looked upon thereafter to their full content.</p>
            <p>Nay ſome do think that their own reaſon will perſwade them, that the beſt game they have to play, is for them to appear forwardeſt in that courſe things now ſo naturally tend to, and ſo get the ſtart of them, whom of late they have ſo much envied: and highly oblige him, from whom the moſt certain and permanent preferments are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, in doing that abſolutely, which perhaps ſome do aym to do by halfes, which certainly, as the whole Nation and each County wherein they quarter, are now inclined, were no hard matter for them to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119590:5"/>
            <p>The Generality of the Phanatiques alſo conſidering, that although there be ſome number of them, yet they being moſt but of ſmall wealth, and intereſt in the Nation, which having conceived a great odium, and jealouſy of their principles, and deſignes, and having of late had ſome diſcovery of our actings with them, would be very ready and earneſt to oppoſe their leaſt attempt: And they beleiving the indulgence and compaſſion that thoſe, who are now coming to power, would have of their errours and weakneſſe: And how in all prudence &amp; policy, for many Years, there can be no rigid courſes taken againſt any party whatſoever, except they give a juſt provocation by ſome deſperate attempt, are reſolved (we feare) to acquieſſe likewiſe. Nay the whole Kingdome is ſo charmed, with the expectation they have of the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parliament, which being likely to conſiſt of men of integrity and ample eſtates, the enjoyment of which in peace, and free from impoſition, muſt needs be ſuch their and the whole Nations true intereſt, that there is ſcarce any hopes left to us, but that they are generally and cheerefully reſolved to ſubmit to their determination.</p>
            <p>The ſubſtance of what I write to you I have from as able and active a head, on our behalfe now there upon the place, as any <hi>Europe</hi> affords, to be the preſent poſture of affaires in <hi>England,</hi> which no little augments all our troubles, nor could I forbeare communicating of it unto you, for your ful information, knowing you are as fit as any man to have your ful ſhare in acting ſome things that are yet thought upon to prevent (if poſible) thoſe contingencyes, ſo unhappy and diſaſtrous to us, of which I ſhall ſhortly ſend one to you that ſhall give you an account.</p>
            <p>Procure me Sir I beſeech you if you can, the ſecond Tome of <hi>Eſcobars morall Theology,</hi> the <hi>Lyons</hi> edition, and <hi>Du Puis</hi> his <hi>doctrina vera</hi> lately printed with you at <hi>Paris.</hi> And take heed what communication you keepe with the Cure of <hi>St. Roch,</hi> and <hi>Monſier de Ruſſe,</hi> becauſe to my knowledge they keep great correſpondence with the <hi>Janſeniſts.</hi> This is all at preſent which I thought fit to trouble you with; I commit you therefore to the protection of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> our <hi>Bleſſed Lady,</hi> and all the <hi>Holy Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Doway <date>27 March, 1660. <hi>Stilo novo.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
